But what you could do with nuclear weapons
is use a small number of them
to convince the other side
that you were deadly serious
The West is leading
Ukraine down the primrose
path, and the Israelis
are executing a genocide in Gaza.
It's not China's fault
that it wants to be powerful.
So if you get into trouble
and you dial 911,
there's nobody at the other end.
Hi this is John Mearsheimer
And what I'd like to talk about
today is nuclear weapons
and in particular,
tactical nuclear weapons.
There have been a lot of reports
in the press
that the United States
is very interested in, quote unquote,
expanding its options
when it comes to nuclear use.
And in that context,
there has been much talk
about relying more on tactical
nuclear weapons
for purposes of deterrence
and for purposes of war
fighting moving forward.
And I'd like to talk about this issue
of tactical nuclear weapons
and what's going on here.
What's driving this interest
in tactical nuclear weapons
and whether or not it makes sense
now with regard to what's driving
the interest in tactical nuclear weapons?
I think, first of all,
there's no question that the United States
is very interested in having many options
when it comes to employing its nuclear
forces.
You want to remember that
when the United States
first developed its nuclear arsenal
after World War Two,
and especially in the 1950s,
it employed a policy
of massive retaliation.
And there was not
there were not a lot of options
built in to the American
doctrine for employing nuclear weapons.
Again,
the emphasis was on massive retaliation,
not flexible response or flexible options.
But as time went by,
certainly starting in the late
1950s, early 1960s, we began to think
long and hard about just having
a lot more flexibility in terms
of how we use those nuclear weapons.
So I find it hardly surprising that
the United States is interested
in expanding its options
from that perspective.
But I actually believe
that's not the main force driver here.
I believe what really matters
is that we have discovered,
as a consequence of
the Ukraine war,
and especially the Iran war,
that our conventional forces
are much weaker
relative to our principal adversaries
than we recognized a few years ago.
I think what happened here
is that during the unipolar moment,
the United States
basically allowed its industrial
base to wither away.
And we discovered
in the Ukraine war
that if you get involved in a conflict
with a country like Russia,
and this is true of China as well,
you need a robust industrial base
to produce the weaponry to wage that war.
One of the advantages that the Russians
have over the Ukrainians,
and even over the Europeans
and the Americans, is that the Russians
have a robust industrial base
so they can produce weaponry
over the long term for purposes
of waging a protracted conflict.
If the United States
were to get involved in a war with China.
China has a robust industrial base
and it can continue.
It could continue that war for years
on end.
The United States would be in deep trouble
after a few months because, again,
it does not have
a sufficient industrial base
to wage a protracted conventional war.
And then, of course,
if you go to the Iran war, it's very clear
that we have run down our stockpile
of precious, precious munitions
in that conflict.
And the end result
is that our conventional deterrence
has been has been weakened.
You always want to remember that
if you're the United States or any other
great power and you're thinking
about deterring an adversary,
you rely on both conventional deterrence
and nuclear deterrence,
and you pay careful attention
to what the balance is
between conventional deterrence
and nuclear deterrence.
And I'll talk more about that
as we go along.
But we're in a situation now, the United
States, where our conventional forces
have been greatly weakened
as a result of the Iran war
and as a result of supplying
the Ukrainians with weaponry.
And furthermore, as I said,
we also realized that we do not have
a robust industrial base,
which would put us at a disadvantage
in a protracted conventional war.
So, given
that our conventional deterrence
has been weakened,
it's hardly surprising
that people are now beginning
to pay more attention
to nuclear deterrence,
because that's the way this works
and what's going on.
Apparently,
is that a lot of people seem to think
that if we emphasize nuclear deterrence,
we should pay careful attention.
Or maybe special attention is a better way
to put it to tactical nuclear weapons.
The tactical nuclear weapons
are well suited
for use on the battlefield.
If you get involved in a war,
whether it's in Europe or in East Asia,
and you don't feel that you have
sufficient conventional forces,
you can fight that war
with with tactical nuclear weapons.
I don't think this is true.
I think this kind of thinking
is misguided.
And I'd like to make the case for why
I think that's the case.
And the best way to do
it is to go back to the 1950s,
which is a period where we emphasized
employing
tactical nuclear weapons
and talk about our experience
in the 1950s,
and to focus laser like on a particular
operation that took place.
This was a war game called Carte Blanche
that took place in June of 1955.
It ran from June 20th, 1955
to June 28th, 1955.
Talk about Carte Bosch.
But before I get to carte blanche,
I just want to paint a broad stroke
picture of how we thought about deterrence
in Europe in the 1950s.
The United States and its allies,
of course, were interested
in deterring the Soviet Union.
And when you talk about deterrence,
it's important to understand
that you also have to be concerned
with warfighting,
because deterrence might not work.
Deterrence might fail.
And if deterrence fails,
then you have to fight a war.
So the United States throughout the 1950s
thought long and hard
about had deter the Soviets
from attacking into Western Europe.
And should deterrence fail.
How to fight a war
against the Soviet Union.
Now, the problem that the Americans
faced from their perspective
was that the Soviet Union had a formidable
conventional army.
Remember,
the Soviet Union played the principal role
in defeating the Wehrmacht
in World War Two.
So throughout the 1950s, most Western
defense experts or Western policymakers
viewed the Soviet military
and especially the Soviet army,
as a formidable force.
Furthermore, it's very important
to understand that West Germany,
which eventually became a key player
in the NATO
alliance, did not become a member of NATO
until 1955, and it did not
begin rearming until 1955.
So from the period from 1950 to 1955.
There was in effect no German army.
Furthermore, the French were busy fighting
against the Vietnamese in Indochina.
You remember the famous
battle of the NBN Phu,
which put an end to the French position
in Vietnam, took place in 1954.
So France was distracted
in a very important way.
There was no German military
of any consequence,
and the United States had limited forces
in Europe, limited conventional forces.
So what we decided to do in the 1950s
was to deploy large numbers
of tactical nuclear weapons
to Europe and rely
heavily on tactical nuclear weapons,
not only for deterrence purposes,
not only to deter
a Soviet conventional attack,
but for war fighting purposes as well.
And by the way,
this is why the United States
has never had a no first use policy.
The United States has never had a
no first use policy,
because it is always understood
that it might have to use nuclear weapons
to rescue the situation.
If it was losing a conventional war
against the Soviet Union.
So in the 1950s,
when NATO conventional forces
were not especially strong
and the Soviet Union
presented a formidable threat.
We believed that
if deterrence failed
and the Soviets were to attack,
we would have to turn to nuclear weapons
very quickly, if not immediately.
So it's just very important to understand
that tactical nuclear weapons
were seeing for much of the 1950s
as a magic weapon.
Now, what happened to throw
cold water on this whole line of thinking
was a war game that was run
in mid June 1955.
This is called carte blanche, and
we had the situation where the Soviets
would attack with conventional forces.
We would use nuclear weapons,
tactical nuclear weapons in response.
And of course, the Soviets
would use nuclear weapons of their own.
Now, what happened in this war game,
basically about 3000
NATO aircraft
from 11 different countries were employed
in the war game. And
about,
I'd say, 335
nuclear weapons were employed.
The usual range is 335 to 355.
That's how many tactical nuclear weapons
were employed in this war game.
And by the way,
the Russians, of course, employed
nuclear weapons as well as the NATO forces
in this war game.
And in fact,
the Russians or the Soviets ended up
using or deploying or
exploding more nuclear weapons, slightly
more nuclear weapons than Naito did.
But let's say the total was about 335
nuclear weapons.
And the war was fought
almost exclusively on West German soil.
Now, what was the end result?
The end result is that 1.7
million Germans died, West Germans
died, and 3.5 million
West Germans were wounded.
Moreover,
these numbers don't take into account
the subsequent deaths that would occur
as a result of the radiation poisoning.
So you just want to think about that.
You had a war game
that went from June 20th to June 28th.
This is 1955, the middle of the 50s,
and it ended up with 1.7
1.7 million West Germans dead.
What is this tell you?
In effect,
it tells you that you're destroying
Germany to save Germany.
This operation,
this war game, was viewed
as evidence that it was hard to see how
you could defend West
Germany with tactical nuclear weapons
without destroying it
as a functioning country.
And it raised all sorts of
concerns, unsurprisingly,
in West Germany,
about whether this was a viable strategy
for defending Germany
or defending Western Europe
against a possible Soviet attack.
When people calculated how much
destruction had resulted from this war
game, it became clear to many people
that given this level of destruction,
tactical
nuclear weapons did not make much sense.
There was another dimension
that came into play here
that really mattered.
And that's the issue of escalation.
In the war game itself.
It became very clear that it was hard
to control escalation. And
there is no question that
it's hard to draw a clear line
between tactical nuclear weapons,
intermediate range
nuclear weapons
and strategic nuclear weapons.
And not only is it hard to draw
that line, it's a slippery slope
so that once
you start using tactical nuclear weapons,
you quickly
find yourself in a situation
where you're thinking about using
intermediate range nuclear weapons
or strategic nuclear weapons.
On top of that, because we
thankfully have never had a nuclear war.
We have very little understanding
of the dynamics of escalation
in a nuclear war.
And you want to understand that
in a nuclear war, if you're interested in
limiting it to West Germany here,
we're talking about the NATO scenario.
You need excellent command and control.
And that's true in any nuclear war, right?
If you want to keep it limited,
you have to have excellent command
and control systems.
And there's all sorts
of evidence that it'll be
very difficult,
if not impossible, to maintain
meaningful command and control
as you go up the escalation ladder
in a nuclear conflict.
So what happens after carte blanche
is we come to realize
that tactical nuclear weapons
really are not a viable way
of defending West Germany
because of the destruction
that would be wrought on that country.
And furthermore,
we come to quickly understand
that the threat of escalation is
so great that you can't allow yourself
to think that you can fight
a limited nuclear war of the sort
that played out in carte blanche
and keep it limited.
And indeed, there is a serious possibility
that if you were in real life
to engage in a war
in West Germany and
the NATO forces
and the Soviet forces of the Warsaw
Pact forces were to use
significant numbers of nuclear weapons,
it wasn't clear that you could keep it
limited.
In fact, there was
there were all sorts of reasons
to think it would escalate
to a general thermonuclear war, which,
of course, nobody wanted anything
to go back to the 50s.
What happens is that in 1957,
amazingly, two years after
Carte Blanche, NATO formalizes
a military doctrine.
It's called MC 14 two.
NATO formalizes a military doctrine
which calls for mass abuse
of nuclear weapons to defend Europe,
and places a great emphasis
on using tactical nuclear weapons.
That's MC 14 two and that's
that's approved by NATO in the spring
of 1957, two years after Carte Blanche.
But then what begins to happen over time
is that NATO begins to rethink this issue,
given what happened with carte blanche,
and given all the studies
that are subsequently done
on the subject of escalation
and nuclear flexibility,
we begin to realize that.
A doctrine for defending Europe
that relies on tactical nuclear weapons
is not a good idea.
In fact, it's a very bad idea.
So two things happen here.
The first is that NATO decides
that it's going to emphasize
conventional deterrence
much more in the future
than it had in the past.
Remember
I said before that if you're a great power
and you're thinking about how to deter
an adversary,
you have to think about the balance
between conventional deterrence
and nuclear deterrence.
How much do you want to rely on
conventional deterrence?
How much do you want
to rely on nuclear deterrence?
There's no question, given that we live
in a nuclear world, that nuclear
deterrence and conventional deterrence
are both going to be present all the time.
But the question is, what is the balance
look like between the two?
And what I'm telling you
is that during the 1950,
the balance was heavily skewed in favor
of nuclear deterrence in Europe.
And this, of course, is
seen in MC 14 two,
which is the NATO doctrine
that's put into place
in the spring of 1957.
But what happens over time
is that NATO de-emphasize
its reliance on nuclear deterrence,
and it begins to build formidable
conventional forces,
and it begins to rely much more
on conventional deterrence.
And this is possible in good part
because the German army
comes online after 1955.
Remember, Germany joins NATO in 1955
and Germany rearmed in 1955,
where it starts rearmament in 1955.
This is the same year, same time
frame as carte blanche.
And what happens over the course
of the second half
of the 1950s, in the early
1960s, is the Germans develop
a very formidable fighting force,
conventional fighting for us.
Remember, the Germans
did not have nuclear weapons at the time.
The Germans, of course,
still have no nuclear weapons.
But the Germans had a very formidable
conventional army.
And the United States commits to building
more powerful conventional forces
in Europe as well.
And we begin to de-emphasize
nuclear deterrence, which is another way
of saying we begin to de-emphasize
our emphasis on tactical nuclear weapons.
And we rely much more on
conventional deterrence.
Now, the second thing that we do
is that we fully understand
that we want to continue
to rely on nuclear deterrence.
If conventional deterrence
and nuclear deterrence fail
to stop the Soviets from attacking
and the Soviets attack,
we will first try to stop them
conventionally.
This is what happens in the 1960s.
We decide by then that if the Soviets
attack into Western Europe,
we will first try to stop them
with the formidable conventional forces
that NATO built up in the late 50s
and in the early 1960s.
And you want to remember that
back in the mid 50s,
at the time of court, Blanche,
if the Soviets were to attack,
we would almost automatically
go to using tactical nuclear weapons.
There's
no real conventional deterrence there.
For warfighting purposes.
We were going to rely on
tactical nuclear weapons.
That all changes by the early 1960s.
And of course, we're relying
on conventional deterrence.
But everybody fully understands
that there's a possibility
that the conventional forces will fail
to stop the Soviets
and the Soviets and their allies,
and the Warsaw Pact
will overrun Europe, Western Europe.
So the question that NATO then faces is,
how should it
think about using its nuclear weapons?
Now everybody remembers
what happened with carte blanche, right?
So there's no incentive
to fight a conventional war.
Let me put it differently.
To fight a war, a failed conventional war
with tactical nuclear weapons
in West Germany.
So there's no incentive to massive use
of tactical nuclear weapons.
Should the conventional forces
of NATO fail
to stop the Warsaw Pact
conventional forces.
So what NATO does is
come up with a clever doctrine.
It says that should
the Warsaw Pact begin to overrun NATO's
conventional forces, what NATO will do is
it will deploy a handful
of nuclear weapons against targets,
maybe in East Germany,
maybe in Czechoslovakia, maybe in Poland,
just a handful of nuclear weapons
to convey to the Soviet Union
that it was deadly
serious about stopping the war
and preventing the Warsaw Pact
from overrunning all of Europe.
In other words, what NATO planned to do
was to launch
a very limited nuclear attack
for throwing both sides
at on the slippery slope to oblivion.
NATO was not interested
in launching a handful of nuclear weapons
to win the war in any military sense,
NATO had figured out,
as a result of carte blanche
and the subsequent analysis that was done,
that you could not win a war
with nuclear weapons.
But what you could do with nuclear
weapons is use a small number of them
to convince the other side
that you were deadly serious
about coercing them to stop their attack,
and it was really the threat of escalation
that was at the heart of this strategy.
In other words, the idea was that if
you used the handful of nuclear weapons,
there would be an ever present threat
of further escalation
if the Soviets didn't
stop their conventional offensive
against Western Europe,
the United States would use
maybe a few more nuclear weapons.
And who knows where this would lead.
So you see that what happens is
that it's not the tactical nuclear weapons
or small nuclear weapons disappear.
What happens is that NATO
thinks about using those nuclear weapons
in a much more limited way, in a way
that has really nothing to do with war
fighting.
MC 14 slash two.
This is the 1957 version
of NATO strategy
on the employment of nuclear weapons.
MC 14 two basically calls
for war
fighting with tactical nuclear weapons.
If you look at MC 14 three,
which is adopted by NATO
in 1967, ten years later,
it calls for using nuclear weapons
in a very limited way
for purposes of basically
putting both sides out
on the slippery slope to oblivion
and convincing the Soviets
or the Warsaw Pact in this case,
that it should stop its offensive
against Western Europe,
because the United States will increase
the number of its attacks
with nuclear weapons
if the Soviets don't stop, and
at some point this could escalate into a
a general thermonuclear war
that the Soviet
Union certainly does not want.
Now, there are many people
who think that NATO strategy,
as laid out in MC 14
three, makes no sense.
That's an issue for another day.
The point that I'm trying to make here
is that the United States of America,
once upon a time, placed a great emphasis
on nuclear deterrence
and nuclear war
fighting with tactical nuclear weapons.
And the logic that was employed in
that case had to do with the fact
that we did not feel that
we had sufficient conventional forces
to deter or fight the Soviet Union.
We didn't have sufficient nuclear
excuse me.
We didn't have sufficient
conventional deterrence, and therefore
we had to rely on nuclear deterrence,
which in effect meant employing
tactical nuclear weapons.
But it quickly became clear
with carte blanche
that was simply not a viable strategy.
And we moved away from it.
And again,
we moved away from it in two ways.
And by the way,
those two ways all were placed
under the umbrella
of flexible response, right?
The first way we moved away from
it was we increased
our conventional capabilities
on the central front in Europe.
We shifted the balance
between nuclear deterrence
and conventional deterrence
in favor of conventional deterrence.
Number one and number two,
we abandoned the idea that you could fight
a nuclear war with tactical
nuclear weapons in in Europe.
And we instead adopted this policy
to use Thomas Schelling's language.
Would
that might be called manipulation of risk.
We were using a handful of nuclear weapons
to manipulate
the Soviets by by threatening
the possibility of escalation
to the general thermonuclear level.
Now, what does this tell us
about the situation that we're in today?
It tells us that we're in a lot of trouble
because our conventional forces
have been weakened,
and therefore there is powerful incentive
to rely more on nuclear deterrence
than we have on the path in the past,
or at least since the 1950s.
And this is not a good thing.
You want to have a deterrent posture
that relies on conventional
forces and nuclear forces, but you want
the nuclear forces in the background.
You want the conventional forces up front.
But the problem we face,
and this is certainly true in East
Asia today, is that we are in a position
where our conventional forces,
our conventional deterrent,
is nowhere near as formidable
as it should be for a variety of reasons
that are subject for another day.
And therefore we're relying
or thinking about relying more
on nuclear deterrence.
And of course, this has pushed us
to think about tactical nuclear weapons.
But as Carte blanche shows,
this is not a viable strategy.
There's no way the United States
can fight a war with tactical nuclear
weapons in Europe or in East
Asia, and win
that war in any meaningful way.
Carte blanche shows that very clearly,
and nothing has changed since then.
And furthermore,
the threat of escalation is ever present.
So all of this is to say that
what the United States should do
moving forward,
instead of relying on tactical
nuclear weapons
for warfighting purposes, is get back
to the business of building up
its conventional deterrent
and thinking about using nuclear weapons,
if need be, in a much more selective
and coercive way of the kind
that is embodied in MC
14 three, which, as I said,
became NATO doctrine and 1967.
That concludes my episode for today.
I'm quite confident
that there'll be many more episodes down
the road that deal with different aspects
of the nuclear issue, because there's
almost no question that given
the way events are evolving in the world
today, nuclear issues of all sorts
will become much more important
to talk about
than has been the case in recent decades.
Thank you very much for listening,
and I look forward to our next episode.